<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The support of the faithful in times of persecution, or, A sermon preach'd in the wilderness to the poor Protestants in France by M. Brousson ... ; faithfully translated from the French.</title>
            <title>Confiance du fidèle persécuté. English</title>
            <author>Brousson, Claude, 1647-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3102</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12782529</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12782529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93841</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93841)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 708:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The support of the faithful in times of persecution, or, A sermon preach'd in the wilderness to the poor Protestants in France by M. Brousson ... ; faithfully translated from the French.</title>
                  <title>Confiance du fidèle persécuté. English</title>
                  <author>Brousson, Claude, 1647-1697.</author>
                  <author>Rogers, Timothy, 1658-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 82 [i.e. 28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Snowden for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation by Timothy Rogers of "La confiance du fidèle persécuté", one of the sermons in "La manne mystique du désert".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XLI, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93841:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Support of the Faithful IN <hi>Times of Perſecution.</hi> OR, A SERMON Preach'd in the Wilderneſs TO THE Poor Proteſtants in FRANCE.</p>
            <p>By M. <hi>Brouſſon,</hi> an Eminent Miniſter, who was broke upon the Wheel at <hi>Montpelier, Nov.</hi> 6. N. S. 1698.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated from the French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Snowden,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93841:2"/>
            <head>IT is hop'd the <hi>Reader</hi> will not be diſpleaſed with theſe following Paſſages, as not altogether unſuitable to this Diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>True Chriſtianity is not only the beſt, but the beſt natur'd Inſtitution in the World; and ſo far as any Church is depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from good Nature, and become Cruel and Barbarous, ſo far it is degenerated from Chriſtianity. [A. B. <hi>Tillotſon's</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Vol. III. 2 Edit. p. 26.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I have learnt from the antient Fathers of the Church, that <hi>nothing is more againſt Religion than to force Religion,</hi> and of St. <hi>Paul, The Weapons of the Chriſtian Warfare are not Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> And great reaſon; for humane Violence may make Men counterfeit, but cannot make them believe, and is therefore fit for nothing but to breed Form without, and Atheiſm within. Beſides, if this means of bringing Men to embrace any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion where generally uſed (as if it may be juſtly uſed in in any place by thoſe that have power, and think they have Truth, certainly they cannot with Reaſon deny, but that it may be uſed in every place, by thoſe that have power as well as they, and think they have truth as well as they) what could follow but the maintenance perhaps of Truth, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps only of the Profeſſion of it in one place, and the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of it in a hundred? What will follow from it, but the preſervation peradventure of Unity, but peradventure only of Uniformity, in particular States and Churches; but the immortalizing the greater and more lamentable Diviſions of Chriſtendom and the World? And therefore what can fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from it, but perhaps in the Judgment of Carnal Policy, the Temporal Benefit and Tranquility of Temporal States and Kingdoms, but the infinite prejudice, if not the deſolation of the Kingdom of Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:93841:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Groans</hi> of our poor <hi>diſtreſs'd Brethren</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> have for ſeveral Years paſt, reached our Ears, and toucht our Hearts, and I hope many pious Souls have not failed daily, and with fervor, to commit their ſad caſe to God, and to beg of him Support and Conſolation, for ſo many miſerable People. Our Relation to them in the Profeſſion of the ſame <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> the <hi>common Tenderneſs of humane Nature,</hi> and the <hi>ſhare that we ought to have in their Sorrows,</hi> by vertue of that Precept of St. <hi>Paul, To weep with them that weep,</hi> do all oblige us to think of them with the greateſt Compaſſion, and to pray, that either the <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cup may paſs from them,</hi> or be <hi>ſweetned</hi> with the Love of God; and that when their Tryals are encreaſed, their Faith and Patience may be ſo too. For the <hi>Furnace</hi> is newly heated, and the <hi>Cloud</hi> over them more thick and diſmal, as will appear to any one that reads the Declaration, given at <hi>Verſailles</hi> the 13th of <hi>Decemb. 1698.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' theſe bleſſed Servants of God are greatly afflicted, yet they are not forſaken. They have <hi>Manna in the Deſart;</hi> of which the <hi>Reader</hi> has a taſte in the following <hi>Sermon.</hi> The Honeſty, and Sincerity, and Love to the Souls of Men, which appears in every part of it, will make a ſufficient Apology for ſeveral things that a <hi>curious Reader</hi> might expect. There is in this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> a warm Zeal, and an Eloquence ſuited to the Condition of the Preacher and his Hearers. People in <hi>deep Mourning</hi> do not affect Finery, but wear a grave ſolemn Dreſs. The <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> has not thoſe Varieties that are to be found in <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Courts;</hi> but the <hi>Faithful,</hi> that are perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake, find there <hi>ſweet Refreſhments</hi> and <hi>Conſolations:</hi> And <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt did not ſtarve, when he fed upon <hi>Locuſts</hi> and <hi>wild Honey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:93841:3"/>This Sermon was preach'd in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> by M. <hi>Brouſſon,</hi> and taken out of a Volume of ſeveral Sermons, Printed in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and approv'd by the French Synod, held at <hi>Haerlem,</hi> in the Year <hi>1695.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How exemplary the Converſation of this bleſſed Man was, how convincing his Doctrine, and how ſuitable to miniſter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to his poor Brethren, as alſo with what admirable Zeal and Conſtancy he triumph'd over all Dangers, and over Death its ſelf, will appear when his <hi>Life</hi> is publiſh'd, which is promiſed to the Publick by thoſe that were acquainted with him, &amp; we expect with great earneſtneſs, as knowing many remarkable and uſeful things, as well as extraordinary, muſt be in the Life of ſo great a Man; who, whilſt he lived, preached under the Croſs, and died with a Patience and Conſtancy, ſuited to the chearful Hopes that he had of a glorious Eternity; where he now reſts from his Labours and his Pains, and where all his Tears are wiped away.</p>
            <p>If this Sermon, which was tranſlated from the Original in <hi>French,</hi> meet with acceptance, the Reader may expect more in due time; and methinks ſuch Sermons muſt come with a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar advantage, which were preach'd by ſuch an one, as ſeal'd with his Blood, the Doctrine that he taught; He ſat in bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and has left heat and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmth behind him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Reading of this Diſcourſe may do good to many Souls, is the Prayer of,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tim. Rogers.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93841:3"/>
            <head>THE Support and Confidence OF BELIEVERS IN <hi>Times</hi> of <hi>Perſecution</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH XLI. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Fear not, thou Worm <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ye Mortal Men of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> I will help thee, ſaith the Lord, and thy Redeemer is the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Beloved Brethren in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the 7th Chapter of <hi>The Book of</hi> Job, that Holy Man ſays,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Engliſh Verſion,</hi> An appointed time to Man upon Earth.</note> 
               <hi>That the State ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Mortals upon Earth, is a ſtate of Warfare,</hi> and that their Days, are as the days of a Hireling. And 'tis ſo in effect, for Men ſpend their Time in continual Labour, Trouble and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93841:4"/>
Inquietude. But if that be true, with reſpect to all Men in general, 'tis more peculiarly ſo with reſpect to the Faithful: For their whole Life is but one conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Combate, againſt the Fleſh, the World, and the Devil. God makes them very often undergo very rude and ſevere Tryals. <hi>Many are the Afflictions of the Righteous,</hi> ſays <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 34.19. The Days of the Faithful are few and evil, as thoſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <hi>Jacob</hi> of old. The Faithful are in continual Troubles and Alarums. If they were of the World, the World would love them; but becauſe they are not of the World, the World hates and perſecutes them. They are generally weak and feeble, but their Enemies are powerful and terrible, after the Fleſh; and thence 'tis that the Righteous are ſo often oppreſs'd.</p>
            <p>And the God of infinite Wiſdom thinks fit it ſhould be ſo, <hi>my beloved Brethren,</hi> in order to humble us, to reduce us from our Wandrings, to diſengage us from the World, to exerciſe our Faith and Patience, to force us to have recourſe to him in our Afflictions, and to put our Confidence in him, to make us taſte of the Conſolations of his Spirit, and at the ſame time to convince us, that his good Providence takes care of his Children in their Streights and Neceſſities; and, in fine, to make us admire the wonderful Deliverances he vouchſafes to give them, when they have profited by his Chaſtiſements, and have glorified him in the time of their Tryal. And therefore now he ſays in our Text, <hi>Fear not, thou Worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ye Men of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>I will help thee, ſaith the Lord, and thy Redeemer is the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93841:4"/>Now to underſtand well the Senſe of theſe Words and of the other Prophecies of the old Teſtament, we are to obſerve, that ſince the Jewiſh Church was the Type of the Chriſtian, and the ſame things that befel the Jewiſh Church were to befal the Chriſtian; we muſt obſerve, I ſay, that though the literal Senſe of the Prophecies of the Old Teſtament had reſpect to the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the Fleſh; yet their My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Senſe relates to the Chriſtian Church, which is <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the Spirit; and moreover, that thoſe ancient Prophecies have their chief and full Accompliſhment no where but in the Chriſtian Church. They that take this remark along with them, as they read theſe antient Prophecies, will make wonderful Diſcoveries of what ſhould fall out in the Chriſtian Church: In the general, they'l find there, that the Chriſtians would be corrupted by Proſperity as the Jews were before them. That they would plunge themſelves even in the Idolatry of the Gentiles; and that afterwards theſe Idolatrous Chriſtians would for a great while oppreſs the Faithful Servants of God that Worſhip him in Purity according to his Word; but that God would relieve them at laſt, and deliver them out of all their Troubles. And to this purpoſe God ſpeaks to his deſtitute People in the Verſes afore my Text; <hi>Fear thou not,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for I am with thee; be not diſmay'd, for I am thy God; I will ſtrengthen thee; yea, I will help thee; yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my Righteouſneſs. Behold, all they that were incens'd againſt thee, ſhall be aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: They ſhall be as Nothing; and they that ſtrive with thee ſhall periſh. Thou ſhalt ſeek them, and ſhalt not find them, even them that contended with thee:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93841:5"/>
They that War againſt thee, ſhall be as nothing, and as a thing of nought, For I, the Lord thy God, will hold thy right hand, ſaying unto thee, Fear not, I will help thee.</hi> Whereupon he adds the Words of my Text, <hi>Fear not, thou Worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ye Men of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>I will help thee, ſaith the Lord, and thy Redeemer is the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>I ſhall confine my ſelf to the Myſtical Senſe of theſe Words, and only examine them as they may relate to Chriſtians. And with the aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit, which, I have already implor'd, and do ſtill with all my Soul, I ſhall conſider theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Name God calls his Diſtreſſed People by, <hi>Thou Worm Jacob, Men of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Conſolation he gives them in this their Deſtitute State; <hi>Fear not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I will help thee, and thy Redeemer is the Holy one of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>God grant, my Beloved, we may all meditate on theſe things with due attention; to the end we may receive that Inſtruction and Comfort which the Spirit of God holds forth to us in theſe Words, and is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us in this time of Diſtreſs; wherein all that will ſerve God with Purity according to his word, ſuffer a Cruel and Bloody Perſecution.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93841:5"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>God calls his People here, <hi>Thou Worm</hi> Jacob; or, <hi>Jacob</hi> thou art but a Worm. Now,</p>
               <p n="1">1. When God calls his People, <hi>Jacob;</hi> he would have us conſider them all but as one Man: And in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, all the Faithful together compoſe but one myſtical Body, whereof Chriſt is the Head. They are all unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Holy Spirit, they are all Members of one another; therefore they ought to live in perfect uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and (like the Primitive Chriſtians) love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo entirely as to be but one Heart and one Soul.</p>
               <p n="2">2. True Chriſtians are called <hi>Jacob,</hi> becauſe they are the Poſterity of <hi>Jacob</hi> after the Spirit, and Heirs of his Faith and Piety, and of the Promiſes which God made to him of old. <hi>Jacob</hi> parted with the food that periſheth, that he might obtain the Bleſſing of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and that of his God, together with the Heavenly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments thereto annex'd. In like manner the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ought to abandon all Earthly Advantages, that they may have a ſhare in the Glory and Felicity of Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Believers are call'd <hi>Jacob,</hi> becauſe their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this Life is like that of <hi>Jacobs.</hi> For as <hi>Jacob</hi> who was born after the Spirit, was heretofore Perſecuted by <hi>Eſau</hi> his Elder Brother that was born after the Fleſh: So Faithful Chriſtians that are Chriſtians after the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are likewiſe perſecuted by Antichriſtians who are Chriſtians after the Fleſh. Theſe wicked falſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93841:6"/>
reproach us every now and then, that we are but of Yeſterday. The truth is, more Ancient than they; But with reſpect to our Reformation, which is our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Birth, we grant they are in a ſort older than we, as <hi>Eſau</hi> was older than <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then, as I told you before, they are born after the Fleſh, as <hi>Eſau</hi> was, and we after the Spirit, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> was; and that is the reaſon they perſecute us. And this is no new thing: <hi>Abel</hi> that was born after the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, was perſecuted to Death by his Elder Brother <hi>Cain</hi> who was born after the Fleſh The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Heir of the Promiſe, who was likewiſe perſecuted by his Elder Brother <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> that was born after the Fleſh. So likewiſe the Prophets of old who ſerv'd God with purity according to his word were perſecuted by the Jewiſh Church when it was fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Idolatry. We ought not therefore to be ſurprized that at this time we who adore God in Spirit and in Truth according to his Commandments are in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner perſecuted by a corrupted and Idolatrous Church.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the People of God are not ſimply call'd <hi>Jacob,</hi> but <hi>Thou Worm</hi> Jacob. And in effect, my Friends, we are but Worms of the Earth in the preſence of our God, whoſe greatneſs knows no bounds; for he fills the Heavens and the Earth. Heaven is his Throne, and the Earth is his Footſtool. We are but duſt and Aſhes in compariſon of our great God; nay, we are leſs than the ſmall duſt of the Ballance. Therefore he calls us Worms, that we may always remember our miſery and nothingneſs, that we may always humble our ſelves in his ſight, and never violate that reſpect which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93841:6"/>
is due to his Sovereign Majeſty: But evermore be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a Religious awe in his preſence.</p>
               <p>Further, we are but Worms in compariſon of our Enemies: For generally the Faithful are weak and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picable in human appearance, whereas their Enemies are powerful and formidable in the eſteem of the World.</p>
               <p>Beſides, God calls his People <hi>Men of</hi> Iſrael, or <hi>Iſrael</hi> that are but Men. <hi>Iſrael</hi> you know, my Brethren, is the name God himſelf gave <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he contended with him: This holy Man hearing his Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> was coming out againſt him with four Hundred Men, was put into a great conſternation; therefore he paſſed the whole Night in Supplications and Tears. As he was alone, the Son of God in the ſhape of Man ſtrove with him till break of Day; and when this Divine Perſon ſaw that he could not prevail againſt him, he touched the hollow of his Thigh; ſo that the hollow of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Thigh was out of joynt as he wreſtled with him; and he ſaid, <hi>Let me go, for the Day breaketh:</hi> But <hi>Jacob</hi> anſwered him, <hi>I will not let thee go except thou bleſs me: And he ſaid unto him, what is thy Name? And he ſaid</hi> Jacob; <hi>And he ſaid, thy Name ſhall be called no more</hi> Jacob; <hi>but</hi> Iſrael: <hi>For as a Prince haſt thou power with God and Men and haſt prevailed.</hi> As we read in the 32d of <hi>Geneſis:</hi> So again in <hi>Hoſea, chap.</hi> 12. We read that <hi>By his power he prevailed with the Angel; he wept and made Supplication unto him; he found him in</hi> Bethel, <hi>and there he ſpake with us:</hi> That is to ſay, he contended all the Night with his God by his Prayers and Tears; and by that means he (as it were) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93841:7"/>
the Almighty, and obtained his Favour, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Succour; ſo as that he was delivered out of the aſtoniſhing danger he was in: But God thought fit his Lameneſs ſhould remain, to put him in mind that he ought to humble himſelf continually before God; in order to obtain mercy and relief in all his neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. So God in my Text, when he calls his Afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed People, <hi>Iſrael;</hi> 'tis that he might make us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that when we are benighted in Affliction, as we are at this time, and when we fear the rage and fury of our Enemies; that then it is our Duty to humble our ſelves before God in an extraordinary manner; to repent of all our Sins, and entirely renounce them; and to have recourſe to his Mercy and Grace alone for pardon: and that we ought to ſtrive with him continually by our Prayers and Supplications, till we have diſarmed (as it were) his Almighty Arm, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his Bleſſing and Aſſiſtance; and that for the time to come we ought always to ſet his fear before our Eyes, and to walk humbly with our God all the days of our Life.</p>
               <p>'Tis for this end likewiſe he calls us <hi>Men, ye</hi> Men <hi>of</hi> Iſrael. For thereby he deſigns to put us in mind of the frailty of our Nature, and to make us conſider that ſince our life is in continual danger, either by the fury of our Enemies, or by Sickneſs, or by a thouſand other Accidents to which we are liable; we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Pray without ceaſing, and to throw our ſelves into the Arms of our God, who alone is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and preſerve us in the midſt of all the dangers our life is continually expos'd to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93841:7"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>Now we are to conſider the Conſolation he gives his People under their Sufferings: <hi>Fear not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>thou Worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ye Men of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>I will help thee, ſaith the Lord, and thy Redeemer is the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael. Believers, my Friends, have ſeveral Reaſons to be afraid; but 'tis the Will of God, that they have recourſe to him alone upon all occaſions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Devil uſes all his Efforts to tempt us with the Pleaſures, Riches and Vanities of the World: But then we are to beg of God without ceaſing, that he lead us not into Temptation, but deliver us from the evil One. And at the ſame time we muſt take care our ſelves to avoid the Occaſions of Sin, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate our ſelves from the Places and Perſons that might induce us to offend God. We muſt alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the World, and mortifie our Bodies by mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Sobriety, according to the Words of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Be ſober, be vigilant; for your Adverſary the Devil, as a roaring Lion, walketh about, ſeeking whom he may devour; whom reſiſt, ſtedfaſt in the Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, we muſt read and meditate on the Word of God with continual Application of Mind, and conſtantly pray to God for the aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit; for 'tis by his Word and Spirit he fortifies our Faith, and 'tis by Faith we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to repel all the fiery Darts of the Devil.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93841:8"/>2. If our Sins terrifie us, God commands us to have recourſe to his Mercy and Grace. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his way and live,</hi> Ezek. 33.11. In caſe we are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely converted, ſo as to conceive a ſacred Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for ſin, and heartily renounce all our evil Habits, and ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do good; then the promiſes in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18. <hi>That though our ſins, be as Scarlet, they ſhall be white as Snow; though they be red like Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wool.</hi> To this end we muſt heartily embrace Jeſus Chriſt, as our Saviour, by a firm and lively Faith; for 'tis he that ſuffered death for us upon Earth, and now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes in our behalf in Heaven; 'tis he that is the <hi>Lamb of God which taketh away the ſin of the World,</hi> John 1.29.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If Believers are at any time afflicted with bodily Diſeaſes, 'tis the pleaſure of God, that we apply our ſelves to him as the Sovereign Phyſitian of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as well as Souls; for 'tis he alone that is able to deliver us out of all our Troubles; and has promiſed that all things ſhall work together for our good, <hi>if we do but fear him,</hi> and profit by his Chaſtiſements.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The faithful people of God have likewiſe reaſon to be afraid of the Cheats and Diſguiſes of Falſe Teachers: For, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14, 15. <hi>Theſe falſe Apoſtles are deceitful Workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt. And no marvel,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93841:8"/>
for Satan himſelf is transform'd into an Angel of Light; therefore it is no great thing if his Miniſters alſo be transform'd as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs.</hi> But if Believers conſtantly addreſs themſelves to God for the aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit, God will deliver them out of the Snares of theſe falſe Teachers. <hi>My Sheep,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.28, 29. <hi>ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any pluck them out of my Hand. My Father which gave them me, is greater than all, and none is able to pluck them out of my Father's Hand.</hi> For this end Believers muſt try the Spirits, to know if they are of God. They muſt (like the Antient Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans) examine the Doctrines that are preach'd to them, to know if they agree with the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20. the Word of GOD is the Rule of Knowledge and Truth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In fine, Believers have cauſe to fear the Power and Cruelty of their Enemies. Jeſus Chriſt ſays in the Goſpel, That the Devil is a Murtherer from the beginning. The Miniſters of Satan are alſo Lyers and Murtherers like himſelf. When they cannot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and wheedle a Man into an Error, they perſecute him, and uſe their utmoſt endeavour to ruin him. We read in the Scripture, That the Devil makes uſe of two great means to endeavour to ſhake the Faith of the Elect. To ſome he offers the Glory and Advantages of the World, as he did to our Saviour before; others he ſpoils of their Goods, deprives of their Children, and loads with a thouſand Evils, as he did <hi>Job.</hi> And his Miniſters uſe juſt the very ſame Methods.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93841:9"/>
But as God would not have us ſuffer our ſelves to be ſeduced by Errors and Lies, nor to be led aſide by the Honours and Riches of the World; ſo on the other hand he would have us ſtand firm and impregnable againſt the Power, the Injuſtice and Cruelty of the Enemies of the truth. He requires of us to be always ready to ſuffer all ſorts of Evils and Miſeries for his Service. 'Tis he that has given us all the good things we enjoy in the World; and therefore he expects we ſhould be always diſpoſed to part with them for his Glory: 'Tis he that has given us our Children; and therefore he juſtly requires we ſhould ſubmit to his will when he permits the Enemies of his Kingdom to deprive us of them: He requires us to deliver them up to the care of his wiſe Providence, when they ſtand in competition with our Duty to God. In fine, 'tis he that has given us Being, Life and Motion; and therefore he expects we ſhould be always prepared to ſuffer Death for his Service, whenever he thinks fit to call us to ſuch a Tryal.</p>
               <p>In a word, 'tis God that has given us all things; 'tis therefore very juſt that we ſhould love him above all things. He has created us for his own Glory; 'tis therefore very reaſonable we ſhould glorifie him both by our Life and Death. Jeſus Chriſt has ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Death for us; 'tis very juſt then that we ſuffer ſomething for the advancement of his Kingdom. Our Sins deſerved the Eternal Flames of Hell; 'tis then an act of ſingular favour that God is contented we ſhould but ſuffer a little trouble in this World for his Holy Name ſake. In fine, the Glory and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93841:9"/>
that he prepares for us in Heaven, is it not a ſufficient recompence for all that we can loſe and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his Service upon Earth? <hi>All things duly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, I reckon the Sufferings of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, are not worthy to be compared with the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that ſhall be revealed in us: For this light Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is but for a ſeaſon, worketh for us a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But although God many times permits his People to be oppreſſed by reaſon of their Sins; yet his deſign is not to abandon them entirely: He only deſigns to make them better by his Chaſtiſements, and to cauſe them to return to their God with all their Heart, and put their whole confidence in him. For upon condition we turn to him, and repent of having offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, he alſo repents of having Afflicted us, and Comforts and Delivers us out of all our Diſtreſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fear not,</hi> ſays he in my Text, <hi>thou Worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ye Men of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>for I will help you, ſaith the Lord. thy Redeemer, the Holy one of</hi> Iſrael. The God whoſe aſſiſtance we implore, my Beloved Brethren, is not as the Idols of the Gentiles that can neither ſee, nor hear, nor ſtir to deliver thoſe that invoke them. No, tis the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Heaven and Earth, the Great and Almighty God. He that is Infinitely Good, is ſurely good enough to have pity on our Sufferings: He that is Infinitely Wiſe, is Wiſe enough to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for all our neceſſities: And he that is Almighty cannot want Power to deliver us out of all our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. He is called the <hi>Holy one of</hi> Iſrael, becauſe he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93841:10"/>
is Holineſs it ſelf; and requires us to be Holy as he is Holy: And certainly he that is ſo Holy and Juſt, will not let go unpuniſhed all the injuries that are done to his Glory, all the Evils that his Children are made to ſuffer. He promiſes to help us; who is it then that can hurt us? <hi>If God be for us, who'll be againſt us?</hi> He tells us he is <hi>our Redeemer,</hi> viz. our Defender and Deliverer? what reaſon have we then to be afraid? <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſays <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 27.1, 3. <hi>is my Light and my Salvation, whom ſhall I fear? The Lord is the Strength of my Life, of whom ſhall I be afraid? Though a Hoſt ſhould encamp againſt me, my heart ſhall not fear.</hi> Idolaters indeed put their confidence in Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but the faithful truſt in their God; he is their only Protector and Refuge. And what comfort is it to the Faithful that they have him for their Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whoſe Power knows no bounds? <hi>Bleſſed is the Nation,</hi> ſays <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 33.12. <hi>whoſe God is the Lord; and the People whom he hath choſen for his own Inheritance. Call upon me in the day of trouble, ſays our Great God, Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>I will Deliver thee, and thou ſhalt Glorifie me. Fear not,</hi> ſays he again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43: <hi>for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy Name, thou art mine. When thou paſſeſt through the Waters; I will be with thee; and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee. When thou walkeſt through the Fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the Flame kindle upon thee. For I am the Lord thy God, the Holy one of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>thy Saviour: I gave</hi> Egypt <hi>for thy ranſom,</hi> Ethiopia <hi>and</hi> Seba <hi>for thee:</hi> That is to ſay, I have deſtroyed, and will again deſtroy thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for the love of thee. Then he adds, <hi>Since thou
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93841:10"/>
waſt precious in my ſight, thou haſt been honourable, and I have loved thee; therefore I will give Men for the, and People for thy Life; Fear not, for I am with thee; I will bring thy Seed from the Eaſt, and gather thee from the Weſt. I will ſay to the North, Give up; and to the South, Keep not back: Bring my Sons from far, and my Daughters from the ends of the Earth.</hi> That is to ſay, I have ſuffered you to be oppreſs'd by your Enemies, becauſe of your ſins, and to be diſperſed throughout all the Earth; but when you return to me with your whole Heart, I will, in great Compaſſion, return to you; I will bring you back from the Places of your Exile, and eſtabliſh you in the Land of your Nativity.</p>
               <p>In effect, my Friends, how many Examples have we before our Eyes in the Holy Scriptures of the care God has in all Ages taken of his Children, and of the wonderful deliverances he has vouchſafed to give them, to the end that we may put our Confidence in him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he was but young, was forc'd to leave his Father's Houſe, and to travel all alone into a very diſtant Country, to avoid the fury of his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> that would take away his Life. But the firſt Night he lay on the Road, God appear'd to him in a Dream, and told him, <hi>Behold, I am with thee, and will keep thee in all places whither thou goeſt, and will bring thee again into this Land; for I will not leave thee until I have done that which I have ſpoke to thee of.</hi> And indeed God was always with him; he conducted him ſafe in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93841:11"/>
his Journey; he bleſſed Him; he bleſſed his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; he bleſſed his Family; he brought him again into his own Country, and appeas'd his Brother's Anger.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when he was but a Youth of Seventeen Years, became the Object of the Jealouſie and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of his Brethren. One day as he went to ſee them in the Wilderneſs, they plotted againſt him to put him to death. They threw him into a deep Pit, and afterwards took him up again to ſell him to the <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> who carryed him to <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſold him there for a Slave. Sometime after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being falſly accus'd by his Miſtreſs, he was put in Priſon, and there he lay ſeveral Years. But God at laſt had pity on him, deliver'd him out of his Diſtreſs, and made him Governour of all <hi>Egypt,</hi> then a very powerful Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job,</hi> who was a Holy Man, and one of the greateſt Men of the Eaſt, was ſpoil'd of all his Goods, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of all his Children, and cover'd all over with Ulcers from the Sole of his Foot, to the Crown of his Head, inſomuch that he was forc'd to lie in the Duſt. In this deplorable Condition he ſhould have received (one would think) at leaſt ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from his Wife and intimate Friends. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that, they only encreaſed his Affliction: For his Wife tempted him to murmur againſt God, that he might put an end to his Life: And his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Friends told him, That he muſt have been a Hypocrite and a Wicked Man, ſince God had ſtruck
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93841:11"/>
him in ſo terrible a manner. But at laſt God was mov'd with companion towards him; he deliver'd him out of all his Sufferings and Miſery, reſtor'd his Health, gave as many Children as he had loſt, and Wealth twice as much as he had before, and made him live a hundred and forty Years after his Tryal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David,</hi> who was a Man according to God's own Heart, was alſo perſecuted for a great while toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by King <hi>Saul.</hi> He was forc'd to leave his Wife and Home, and to ſeek for Refuge in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts and Caves, and even there he was ſtill pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by his Enemy. He often found himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to ſuch Extremities, and expoſed to ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Dangers, that he thought it impoſſible for him to eſcape. But he had always recourſe to his God, and God never forſook him. He did wonders to preſerve him in the midſt of ſo many Dangers, and at laſt deliver'd him out of all his Troubles, and exalted him to the Throne of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But above all, who would not admire that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful deliverance, which God wrought for the three young Hebrews, whoſe Hiſtory we read in <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 3. Theſe three faithful Servants of God, having refus'd to proſtrate themſelves before the Idol which King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had made, this proud and mighty Prince, that had before deſtroy'd <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> told them, that if they would not fall down and worſhip this Idol, he would order them to be caſt into a fiery Furnace. And he adds further, <hi>Who is that God that ſhall deliver you out of my hands?</hi> And they anſwered him, <hi>Our God, whom we ſerve, is able to deliver out of the burning fiery Furnace; and he will deliver us out of thy hand, O
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93841:12"/>
King. But if not, be it known unto thee, O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi> As if they had ſaid, We know that our God is Almighty, and able to deliver us, if it ſeems good in his ſight; but if he thinks fit we ſhould die for his Glory, we are all ready to ſubmit and die. Then this proud and cruel Prince, being full of Rage and Fury, commanded that they ſhould heat the Furnace ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times more than it was wont to be heat; and order'd the moſt mighty Men that were in his Army, to bind them, and caſt them into the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fiery Furnace: Which accordingly they did; but the fire conſum'd thoſe that threw them in; and, on the contrary, theſe three faithful Servants of God fell in the midſt of the Flames, without receiving the leaſt damage; the fire did nothing elſe but burn their Bonds; ſo that they walk'd in the midſt of the Flames, without being conſumed. And beſides, there appear'd with them a fourth Man, whoſe form was like the Son of God. Whereupon this Idolatrous King being amaz'd to ſee ſo great a Miracle, made them come forth out of the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and gave glory to the God of Heaven, who had ſo miraculouſly preſerv'd them in the midſt of the Flames, becauſe they had choſe to loſe their Lives, rather than diſpleaſe their God.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelf, becauſe he continu'd to pay to God the Homage due to him, when the King by his Edict had forbid it, was caſt into the Den of Lyons: But God was always with him. He ſhut the Mouths of thoſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Beaſts, ſo that they did him no hurt. And the King ſeeing this Miracle, commanded him to be fetch'd out of the Den, and to throw in his Enemies that accus'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93841:12"/>
him, and they were immediately devour'd by the Lions.</p>
               <p>So when the people of God heretofore groan'd under the Oppreſſion of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> God ſmote <hi>Egypt</hi> with all his <hi>Plagues.</hi> Nay, he ſlew all their Firſt-born; and every Houſe in <hi>Egypt</hi> was in Mourning, and had one died out of it. So again, when the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Army was in purſuit of the people of God, as they were going out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> God covered his people with a Cloud, and divided the Red ſea to let 'em paſs thro' it: But when the <hi>Egyptians</hi> purſued 'em into the middle of the Waters, God caus'd the Sea to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon them, and ſo that great Army was all ſwallow'd up, and not one of them eſcap'd. In ſhort, the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are full of the great wonders that God wrought from time to time for the deliverance of thoſe that fear, and put their whole confidence in him: Therefore ſays he in my Text, <hi>Fear not, thou Worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ye Men of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>for I will help thee, ſaith the Lord, thy Redeemer, the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>What we have ſaid is enough for the Explication of the words; now let us apply what we have heard to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Here we ſee, my beloved Brethren, that all the Faithful are repreſented as one Man, and compoſe but one Myſtical Body; therefore we ought to live together in Union, as being Members one of another. We are all animated by the ſame Spirit, to wit, the Spirit of Chriſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould be all joyn'd together by the Bond of a fervent and unfeign'd Affection: <hi>For by this</hi> (ſays our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.35.) <hi>ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, if you love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We may learn alſo hence, That in order to have a part in the promiſe which God has made, to aſſiſt us, and to be our Deliverer, we muſt be the Spiritual and Myſtical <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that is to ſay, we muſt imitate the Faith and Piety of the Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> whom God himſelf calls
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93841:13"/>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> The promiſes of God, my Brethren, were made to the Patriarchs and their Poſterity; and tho' we are not their <hi>Poſterity after the Fleſh,</hi> yet we are their <hi>Spiritual Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> if we imitate their Faith and Piety.</p>
               <p>Examine your ſelves therefore by this Rule, that you may know whether you are the Children of the Patriarchs, and can claim a Title in the favour of God, in his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and Salvation. If you bear the image of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, if you have their Faith and Piety, if you do their Works, you are their Children, and God will bleſs you, as he did them; he will deliver you out of the Hands of your Enemies; he will load you with his Favours and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and will one day make you partakers of a bleſſed Immortality. But if you imitate not their Example, you are not their Children, and have no ſhare in the promiſes God made to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> when God commanded him to leave his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and part with his Relations, preſently complied with the Will of his God, tho' he knew not where he was to go. And again, when God commanded him to ſacrifice <hi>Iſaac</hi> his beloved Son, he prepar'd himſelf without any more adoe, to execute this dreadful command, having this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, that he could even reſtore his Son to him again, by raiſing him from the dead. And in effect, the Apoſtle takes notice, that he was indeed reſtor'd to him again by a kind of Reſurrection. So <hi>Iſaac</hi> himſelf ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Will of his God, and put himſelf in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to die, as a Teſtimony of his Obedience to him. And <hi>Jacob</hi> was contented to deprive himſelf of the Food that periſheth, in order to obtain the Coeleſtial and Eternal Inheritance: And afterwards he left his Father's Houſe, that he might avoid the violence of his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> who deſign'd to have kill'd him. And ſo likewiſe all the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs did always glorifie God by their Zeal, by their Piety,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93841:13"/>
and by a Pure, Holy, and Unblameable Life.</p>
               <p>God ſets us theſe Examples, to the end we might ſquare our Lives by them, if we would be the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Poſterity of theſe Holy Men, and would have a part in the Promiſes that were made to them. Now when God ſuffers his Church to be perſecuted, he calls upon us to leave our Country and our Friends, to forſake our Goods, and renounce our eaſe and pleaſures, to ſuffer the loſs of our Children, and even to expoſe our Lives for his Glory and Service. Therefore, if we deſire to obtain his Bleſſing, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance and Salvation, we muſt ſubmit to his Will, as the Patriarchs did of old. We muſt alſo glorifie him by a Holy Life, by our Juſtice, our Zeal, our Charity, and Piety: We muſt cauſe our Light to ſhine before Men, that they ſeeing our good Works, may together with us, give Glory to God. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we muſt expect to be treated, not as his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but as Baſtards and Unbelievers.</p>
               <p>What can you expect then, you miſerable World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, whoſe Heart is always bow'd down to the Earth like that of Beaſts; you impenitent Sinners that always perſiſt in your Vices and Diſorders, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and Frauds? You follow the multitude that is running in the broad way to Hell. Therefore if you repent not, you muſt expert to periſh with this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Multitude. You are not the Children of the Patriarchs, ſince you do not their Works. You do the Works of the Devil, that impure Spirit, who is the Father of Lies and Impurity, of Fraud and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and what can you expect, you prophane and rebellious Souls! who, that you might live at your eaſe in your Houſes, and might preſerve your Goods, your Children and your Repoſe, are revolted from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93841:14"/>
God, and continue ſtill in the ſame Spirit of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion? Alas! you are not neither the Children of the Patriarchs, ſince you imitate not their Zeal and Piety, and are not ready to loſe and ſuffer all things, as they were, for the Glory of your God. You do alſo the Works of the Devil, who was the firſt Apoſtate, the firſt Rebel againſt God. Therefore, if you repent not, you ſhall be condemn'd with him to the eternal Flames of Hell. For you are not willing to follow the Example of two or three hundred thouſand Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants of God, who have abandon'd all for his Glory, have left their Country and their Kindred, and parted with their deareſt Friends, and have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expos'd their Lives to great dangers, that they might comply with the Will of their God, and have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in his Favour and Comfort.</p>
               <p>God has for a great while continued to ſend his Faithful Servants to you, to bring you back to your God, and a great many of them have already ſuffer'd death for your ſakes. 'Tis true, you give them a Hearing; but a great many among you perſiſt ſtill in your Vices and Backſlidings. Therefore as many faithful Miniſters, as have preach'd, or do ſtill preach Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to them without ſucceſs, ſhall be ſo many Witneſſes one day in Judgment againſt them, and ſhall condemn them.</p>
               <p>Oh! wretched Sinners that you are! You would enjoy the Pleaſures of the World, like prophane <hi>Eſau:</hi> But you ſhall be depriv'd one day of the eternal Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Paradiſe. You would have your Portion in this Life, but one Day your Portion ſhall be in the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone. You would preſerve your eaſe in this World, but you ſhall be eternally tormented with the Devils in Hell. There
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93841:14"/>
will be weeking and gnaſhing of Teeth: And theſe horrid Puniſhments ſhall never have an end.</p>
               <p>But as for you, Believers, that deſire to have a ſhare in the promiſes of your God, be ye follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Faith, the Piety and Holineſs of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs; and you ſhall receive the Crown of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which God has prepared for all them that fear him, and give glory to his Name. Let us not ſuffer our ſelves to be tempted, my beloved Brethren, by the Criminal Pleaſures of Sin, nor by the Riches and Vanities of the VVorld. Let us pray to God without ceaſing, that he would not lead us into Temptation, but deliver us from the wicked One: And at the ſame time let us diſengage our Hearts from the VVorld, and ſeparate our ſelves from the <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> that may lead us into ſin. Let us mortifie our Bodies by Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Sobriety: Let us continually read and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the VVord of God, that we may become ſtrong in the Faith; and let us evermore beg of God the aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit, that he may make us always walk in his Holy VVays.</p>
               <p>Let us not ſuffer our ſelves to be ſurpriz'd by the ſpecious Pretences of falſe Teachers. They come to us in Sheeps Cloathing, but within they are Ravenous VVolves. At firſt ſight one would think they had the Sweetneſs and Charity of Angels; but no ſooner do the Faithful give them to underſtand that they will not defile themſelves with Idolatry, and that they are reſolved to ſerve God with purity, according to his Commandments; but theſe falſe Teachers diſcover a Cruelty not inferior to that of the moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Beaſts. You will know them by their Fruits,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93841:15"/>
ſays our Saviour. Examine well their Conduct, and you'l ſee that they bear the Image of the Devil. The Devil, as we ſaid before, is <hi>a Liar and a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer from the beginning.</hi> Now theſe falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, are not they Liars like him? Do not they teach Errours and Lies? And do not they ſpread Abroad Fables and falſe Miracles, to ſeduce the Simple and the Ignorant? Have they not likewiſe violated E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts, Treaties of Peace, and the moſt ſolemn Oaths, which are the Pledges and Seals of the Publick Faith? On the other hand, are not they Cruel and Murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as well as the Devil? Do not they every day make the Faithful ſuffer Torments, Martyrdoms and horrible Maſſacres? Do not they likewiſe uſe, on all occaſions, the two great means, which the Devil invented, to endeavour to ſhake the Faith of the Elect? Do not they offer to ſome the Riches and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this World? Do not they propoſe to them Penſions, Offices of the greateſt Truſt and Dignity, and other Worldly Advantages? And do not they ſpoil others of their Goods, take away their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from them, and oppreſs them with a thouſand Evils?</p>
               <p>We muſt therefore, <hi>my beloved Brethren,</hi> refuſe with horrour to hold Communion with theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Satan; and if it be the Will of God that we ſuffer for the Intereſt of his Glory and Service, let us ſubmit to his Sacred Diſpoſal, and prepare our ſelves to loſe and ſuffer all things, that we may give him a Teſtimony of our Obedience and Faithfulneſs. Let us remember that we were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his Glory, and that we ought to glorifie him both in Life and Death. Let us remember that we ought to love him above all that is deareſt to us in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93841:15"/>
the World, more than Father, Mother, Wife, Children, Lands and Vineyards; nay, more than Life it ſelf, if we would be his Children, and deſire to partake of his Salvation.</p>
               <p>Let us conſider well, <hi>my beloved Brethren,</hi> that this Earth is not our Home; that 'tis a Valley of Tears, the place of our Sojourning, full of Miſery and Trouble; and that our True Country is Heaven. The Patriarchs, whoſe Children we are, had not ſo much as where to ſet the Sole of their Feet; they were Pilgrims and Strangers upon Earth; they ſought a City that had ſolid Foundations, whoſe Builder and Founder is God. We muſt therefore renounce all earthly Things, and continually breathe after the Glory and Happineſs of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Let us conſider again, that if God permits us to be perſecuted, 'tis to the end that we may diſcover to the World our Faith, Piety and Conſtancy; and that this Tryal, by which God is glorified, may alſo turn to our own Glory, Salvation and Comfort. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man that endureth Temptation,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James,</hi> ch. 1.12. <hi>for when he is tryed, he ſhall receive the Crown of Life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him. Bleſſed are they that are perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10. <hi>for theirs is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven. Now for a ſeaſon we are in heavineſs, through manifold Temptations: But,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, 1 Epiſt. 1.7, 8, 9. <hi>'tis that the Tryal of our Faith, being much more precious than of Gold that periſheth, may be found unto Praiſe, and Honour, and Glory at the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Jeſus Chriſt: whom having not ſeen, we love; in whom, tho' now we ſee him not, yet believing, we rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory: receiving the end of our Faith, even the Salvation of our Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93841:16"/>Nevertheleſs, <hi>my Friends,</hi> we muſt acknowledge that our ſins are the cauſe of all the Evils we ſuffer. The Churches of <hi>France</hi> were abominably corrupted in their Manners. Therefore God has pour'd out his Judgments upon them and his Wrath is ſtill burning againſt us, becauſe our Repentance is not ſuch as it ought to be. We muſt then, every one of us, turn himſelf from his evil Courſe; and thoſe that have been ſo unhappy as to enter into the Communion of <hi>Babylon,</hi> muſt for ever renounce her Abominations for the time to come. We muſt be poſſeſs'd with a Sacred Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for our Sins, and in a Holy Manner afflict our Souls, and humble our Selves at the Foot of the Throne of the Divine Majeſty; we muſt have recourſe to the Mercy and Grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, who has died for the remiſſion of our Sins. We muſt ſtrive continually with God by our Tears and Supplications, and not let him go till he has bleſſed us; and the good God will at laſt ſuffer himſelf to be overcome by our Cries and Supplications. <hi>Tho' our ſins be as Scarlet, they ſhall be as white as Snow: tho' they be red like Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wool.</hi> Then will he be mov'd by our Miſery to give us Succour and Relief: <hi>He will bow down the Heavens, and come down, and deliver us out of the great Waters that ſurround us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now good Men are oppreſs'd; <hi>He that departeth from evil, maketh himſelf a prey,</hi> Iſa. 59.15. They that would be true to God, ſerve him with Purity, and ſing Praiſes to his Holy Name, are afflicted and perſecuted: whereas Idolaters, the perfidious <hi>Judas's,</hi> the Drunkards, the Laſcivious, the Wicked, the Swearers and Blaſphemers are tolerated and countenanc'd in the World. But theſe diſorders ſhall not always laſt: <hi>Yet a little while, and he that is to come, ſhall come and will not tarry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93841:16"/>Let's take courage then, <hi>my Friends,</hi> &amp; not ſuffer our ſelves to be frighted with the Menaces of the Enemies of the <hi>Truth.</hi> Let us throw our ſelves into the Arms of our God; let us retire under the Shadow of his Wings; let us deliver our ſelves up to the conduct of his wiſe Providence, and put our confidence in him; he promiſes to be our Protector and Deliverer; <hi>and he is faithful in all his Promiſes.</hi> Let us have theſe comfortable words always in our Thoughts, <hi>Fear not, thou Worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ye Men of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>I will help thee, ſaith the Lord, thy Redeemer, the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael. We are but Worms of the Earth, in compariſon of our Enemies; but let us remember, that the Lord of Hoſts, the Great God, is our Strength. VVe are mortal Men, our Life is continually in danger; but let us remember, that he that has Life and Death in his Power, promiſes to aſſiſt and protect us. Let us not be afraid then, ſince he will be our Redeemer and Defender. He commands us to call upon him in our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and promiſes to deliver us out of it, to the end that we may glorifie him; Let us then make him our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; let us cry to him continually; and he'll come to our relief, that ſo we may bleſs him for it, all the days of our Life. God will do wonders for our ſakes, as he has always done in favour of his Children. <hi>For,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>whatſoever things were written afore time, were written for our Learning; that we thro' Patience and Comfort of the Scriptures, might have hope;</hi> that is to ſay, that we may have this confidence in God, that in caſe we imitate the Faith, the Piety, and the Fidelity of thoſe antient Servants of God, whom the Scriptures mention, God will vouchſafe to us the ſame Deliverances, and the ſame Comforts as he vouchſafed to them on the like occaſions.</p>
               <p>He'll reſtore our Children to us again, as he did to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> of old. He'll preſerve our Lives, as he did <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s. He'll be always with us, as he was with <hi>Jacob;</hi> and give
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:93841:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
us the ſame Protection that he gave him. He'll releaſe us out of our Priſons, as he did <hi>Joſeph.</hi> He'll deliver us out of all our Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Miſery, as he did <hi>Job;</hi> and like him, will put us in a happier Condition than that we were in before our Tryal. He'll put an end to all our Troubles, as he did formerly to thoſe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> Now we are in the Furnace, as the three believing <hi>Hebrews</hi> were of old; but God will preſerve us, as he did them, in the midſt of the Flames. The fire of Perſecution will only ſerve to purifie us, and to conſume the Bonds of Sin within us; and he'll bring us out of the Furnace of Affliction, much brighter than we were before. Now we are in the midſt of Lyons, as <hi>Daniel</hi> was of old: But God will ſhut the Mouth of theſe Savage Beaſts; he'll repreſs the Violence of our Enemies, that encompaſs us about on all ſides, and come not behind the very Tygers and Lyons in Cruelty. Now we groan under hard Bondage, as the People of God did heretofore in <hi>Egypt;</hi> but God will deliver us out of it with a ſtrong Hand and ſtretched out Arm. Now we are terrified with the Power of our Enemies; But ſince 'tis againſt God they wage War, God tells us in his Word, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 20.15. <hi>that the Battle is not Our's, but God's;</hi> and that he'll fight for us him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, while we are ſinging Praiſes to his Holy Name, as he fought heretofore for his People in the time of King <hi>Jehoſhaphat.</hi> Now they that afflict us, laugh at us for putting our confidence in God, as if he was not ſtrong enough to deliver us out of their Hands; But God will ſend an Angel to deſtroy them, as he did the Army of the King of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> who blaſphem'd the Lord and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicul'd them that put their confidence in him, as we read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>For this end, <hi>my beloved Brethren,</hi> let us live in the fear of the Lord; let us obey his Holy Commandments; be faithful to him; confeſs his Truth; and continually implore his Mercy, Favour and Relief; and this God will hear our Cries, will hearken to our Prayers, will plead our Cauſe, will help and deliver us, will fill us with his Graces and Comforts, will load us with his Benefits, and will one day take us up to Heaven, to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> us happy for ever with himſelf. Which God of his infinite Mercy grant. Now to Him, Father, Son, and Spirit, one only God beleſſed for ever, <hi>be Honour and Glory, world without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Preach'd in ſeveral places in the Wilderneſs,</hi> 
                     <date>July 23, <hi>and</hi> 31. 1692. <hi>and</hi> Septemb. 14. 1693.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
